Guide to the Jewish Heritage Foundation of North Carolina Collection of Jewish Historical Materials, 1888-2014 RL.10985
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Jewish Heritage Foundation of North Carolina collection of Jewish historical materials
1888-1988, 2014
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Jewish Heritage Foundation of North Carolina
RL.10985
20.5 Linear Feet
Collected by the Jewish Heritage Foundation of North Carolina (JHFNC) from multiple sources, these historical materials document various aspects of Jewish life in North Carolina and beyond. The collection includes individual, family, and organizational/business scrapbooks, medals, certificates, pamphlets, catalogs, correspondence, photographs, and other artifacts and manuscript materials donated to the JHFNC. Topics represented in the collection include Jewish religious education, Jewish history, Jewish social and religious organizations in the United States and North Carolina, and Jewish participation in World War II. The Jewish Heritage Foundation of North Carolina (JHFNC) is an independent organization dedicated to preserving and presenting the history of the Jewish people of North Carolina, and transferred its archives, including these materials, to the Rubenstein Library in 2014.
Historical Note
The Jewish Heritage Foundation of North Carolina (JHFNC) is an independent organization dedicated to preserving and presenting the history of the Jewish people of North Carolina. Through public programming and exhibits, the JHFNC aspires to educate and showcase the richness of Jewish Life as well as promote a familiarity with the culture and lifestyle of Jews to the general public. In 2014, the JHFNC transferred their historical collections, including the materials in the JHFNC Collection of Jewish Historical Materials, to the Rubenstein Library.
Related Material
Jewish Heritage Foundation of North Carolina records, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
North Carolina temple and synagogue historical collection, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Arrangement
The materials in this collection are arranged chronologically.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48-hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Collection Overview
The Jewish Heritage Foundation of North Carolina (JHFNC) Collection of Jewish Historical Materials contains historical materials collected by the JHFNC from various sources as part of its mission to document and preserve the history of Jewish people in North Carolina. The collection includes artifacts, certificates, publications, and other manuscript materials on a variety of topics, including but not limited to religious education, Jewish history, Jewish social and religious organizations in the United States and North Carolina, and Jewish participation in World War II. Types of material include individual, family, and organizational/business scrapbooks, medals, certificates, pamphlets, catalogs, correspondence, and a small amount of photographs. World War II artifacts in the collection include a Nazi officer hat, sword, and daggers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Jewish Heritage Foundation of North Carolina collection of Jewish historical materials was received as a gift as part of the Jewish Heritage Foundation of North Carolina Collection by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University in June 2014.
World War, 1939-1945 -- Participation, Jewish.; Judaism -- History; Jews -- North Carolina -- Social life and customs; Jews -- United States -- Social life and customs; Clippings (information artifacts); Jewish Heritage Foundation of North Carolina
- Jewish Heritage Foundation of North Carolina Collection of Jewish Historical Materials, 1888-1988, 2014
  - Amelie Loeb-Simon [nee Horkheimer] documents, 1888-1950 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Jahrzeit plaque for [Z]erline Goldschmidt, 1902; 20.5 Linear Feet (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Scraps [scrapbook, Goldsmith/Samet], 1910, 1939-1959 and undated (Box 3)
  - Jacob Berman crayon enlargement and pencil sketch, circa 1910-1980 (Box 14)
    Scope and Contents
    Early twentieth-century crayon enlargement of Jacob Berman of Fayetteville, NC. The pencil sketch was created by Harry B. Stein, Berman's grandson, of Fayetteville, NC.
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    Gift of John Gimesh.
  - Baltimore Bargain House catalog, 1911 August (Box 4)
  - Baltimore Bargain House postcard, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Zuckerman family photographs, 1913 and undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Herzl Zion Society, Wilmington, NC - Federation of American Zionists certificate, 1917 March 29 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Gift of B'nai Israel Congregation of Wilmington, NC.
  - Baltimore Bargain House catalog, 1919 June (Box 4)
  - Masonic Appointment Certificate - Solomon Dworsky, 1921 February (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - United Daughters of the Confederacy Certificate - Pauline Kaplan Goldsmith, 1924 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - [Donation to the Academy Shaar Hashamaim in memory of Jacob Sussman], circa 1920s (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - [Kramer's Department Store, Wallace, NC photographs], 1930-1979, 1990 (Box 5)
  - Dramatic moments in Jewish history, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Durham Senior Hadassah yearbook, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - A bird's eye view of Jewish history, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - [Scrapbook - Stein Bros. 50th Anniversary], 1939, 1953 (Box 6)
  - Cashbook - Baugues & Lulp, Route 3, 1939-1950 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Gluck auf Graf Zeppelin!, circa 1930s (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Nazi officer hats, circa 1930s-1940s; 2 items (Box 10)
  - Nazi daggers, circa 1930s-1940s; 3 items (Box 11)
  - Nazi medals, circa 1930s-1940s (Box 12)
  - Nazi sword, circa 1930s-1940s; 1 items (Box 13)
  - [Alien Registration Record - Mrs. S.J. Brown], 1940 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Certificate from the Golden Book of the Jewish National Fund in memory of Jacob Joseph Stein, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - The faith of a Jew, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Certificate from the Golden Book of the Jewish National Fund in memory of Albert Stein Dembo, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - [Kramer's Department Store, Wallace NC clippings], 1944-1995 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - The world over, a magazine for Jewish boys and girls, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - [Pamphlets from Jewish Committee on Scouting], circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - United in service: Women's Organizations' Division tenth annual report, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - National Observance Effort Program Guidelines, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - American Jewish Tercentary Service, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - [Charter members of Leopold Zunz Lodge No. 364, Goldsboro, NC], 1954 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - [Stein Bros. advertisement - "A half-century of service"], 1954 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Book of Life, Temple Sinai, Washington DC, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - The Conservative movement in Judaism, an introduction, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - B'nai B'rith charter, Lodge 2038, Jacksonville, NC, 1955 June 19 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Gift of B'nai Israel Congregation of Wilmington, NC
  - The meaning of passover symbols, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - [Scrapbook - Kinston Sisterhood Hadassah], 1959-1982 (Box 7)
  - [Map of Israel], 1961 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - The Raleigh Chapter of Hadassah yearbook, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Your Jewish heritage [sponsored by Kraft Foods], 1968 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - [Marion H. Lieberman columns and scrapbook], 1975-1979 (Box 8)
  - Biomedical ethics and Jewish law, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - [Program] - Labor Zionist Alliance 32nd annual Third Seder, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Chai: A tribute to Lerner's 18 years, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - A man called David [Bloom], undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - [Plaque honoring Kinston, NC men who served in World War II], undated (Box 9)
  - [United Palestine Appeal check], undated (Box 1, Folder 28)